Preliminary Guide to the Thomas M. Gallie Papers, 1955 - 1972
University Archives Duke University
Thomas M. Gallie papers 1955 - 1972
Gallie, Thomas M.
9.0 Linear Feet 6,000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
Thomas M. Gallie served as Professor of Mathematics and Director of the Computer Science Program at Duke University, and as leader of Triangle Universities Computation Center and the N.C. Educational Computing Services initiatives. The Gallie papers include correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, financial records, and grant proposals. Major subjects include the Duke University Department of Mathematics, the Department of Computer Science, N.C. Educational Computing Services, Triangle Universities Computation Center, computing at Duke University, computing in medical services, and computerized phonetic transcriptions. Materials range in date from 1955-1972.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Thomas M. Gallie Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1972-1974.
Biographical Note
Thomas M. Gallie was born in 1925 in New York City. He was educated at Harvard University (A.B., 1947), University of Texas (M.A., 1949), and Rice University (M.A., 1952, Ph.D., 1954). Gallie came to Duke University in 1954, where he served as a Research Instructor, Assistant Professor, and Professor of Mathematics and Biomathematics (1967-1971). He also held a variety of positions within Duke University's Computer Science Program, including Director of Undergraduate Studies (1974 and 1980), Director of Graduate Studies (1977-1978), and Acting Chair of the department (1982-1984).
In 1965, Gallie became the chair of the Board of Directors of the new Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC), established at Duke University. He served for several years, authoring proposals and implementing new computer systems in Triangle-area universities. The TUCC was a cooperative venture of Duke University, North Carolina State University, and University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill to provide main-frame computing services to the universities, the Research Triangle Institute, and others. The TUCC shut down in 1990 due to financial difficulties, citing the increased use of personal computers, and disagreements among the partners. Although TUCC dissolved, Duke University Computation Center continued. In 1995, the Computation Center became part of the Office of Information Technology.
In addition to his computing work at Duke University, Gallie also held leadership positions with the Microelectronics Center of North Carolina and the North Carolina Educational Computing Service. He was a member of the Mathematical Association of America, the Association for Computing Machinery, Sigma Xi, the Society for International and Applied Mathematics, and the American Association of University Professors. He also served on the Technical Advisory Board of the Durham (N.C.) City Schools. Gallie conducted research in Switzerland and Venezuela, and was a consultant to the Office of Naval Research Committee on Underseas Warfare and the National Science Foundation.
Gallie's major research interests have included pure and numerical mathematics, computer compiler and processor construction, syntax recognition, surface mapping cardiology and electrophysiology, triangulation, hospital and medical functions of computers, computerized phonetic transcription, computer graphics, computer and mathematics education, complex variable theory, numerical analysis, and real-time computing. Gallie is Professor Emeritus of Computer Science at Duke University.
Collection Overview
The Gallie papers include correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, financial records, and grant proposals pertaining to the career of Thomas M. Gallie, the Triangle Universities Computation Center, and computing at Duke University. Materials range in date from 1955-1972.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Computer science -- Study and teaching (Higher)--North Carolina -- Durham
Computer systems -- North Carolina -- Durham
Duke University. Dept. of Computer Science
Duke University. Computation Center
Duke University. Mathematics Dept
Gallie, Thomas M.
Language and languages -- Phonetic transcriptions
Medicine -- Data processing
North Carolina Educational Computing Service
Triangle Universities Computation Center
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Correspondence, 1955-1969, undated (Box 1)
    Personal and professional correspondence regarding North Carolina Computer Education Center, IBM, computers, accounting machines, Duke University Digital Computing Laboratory, North Carolina Computer Orientation Projects. Also includes a large amount of correspondence from Louis Parker of North Carolina Computer Orientation Projects on general curriculum development.
  - Triangle Universities Computing Center correspondence, 1963-1970, undated (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF)-ALGOL Grant, 1961-1963
  - Calculations
  - Character Set 149, 1962-1974
  - ESSO, 1964
  - Myocardial Infarction Research Unit (MIRU), 1967-1968
  - Conference on Computer Education in North Carolina, 1964-1966
  - Math Building, construction proposal, background research, grant notes, 1960-1963
  - National Science Foundation proposals, 1958-1961
  - Association for Computing Machinery (includes U.S. Army Audit Agency), 1957-1964
  - Photograph, "IBM Customer Executive Class No. 6090," 1960
  - Committee on Digital Computers, 1958-1963
  - Publicity letters from user groups
  - Guidance for Users of Integrated Data Processing (Box 3)
  - Budget, 1958-1960
  - National Science Foundation proposal for a Summer Institute at Duke University
  - North Carolina Computer Orientation Project (contains various proposals from N.C. colleges and universities), 1966-1970
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1970
  - Diary of Thomas Gallie, 1959
  - Financial materials relating to grants
  - Computer Planning Committee, 1968-1969
  - Air Force AFSOR 62-164
  - Financial, 1962-1963
  - Duke University Data Acquisition System, proposal
  - IBM proposal, Duke University
  - Triangle Universities
  - National Science Foundation proposal, amendment
  - Budgets, 1958-1960
  - National Science Foundation, Triangle Universities
  - National Science Foundation, Control Data Corporation
  - National Science Foundation, Modernization of the Duke University Digital Computing Laboratory
  - Duke University Computing Laboratory, annual summaries, 1956-1967, 6 bound volumes (Box 4)
    Include correspondence, receipts, reports, instructional manuals, financial materials, and clippings
  - Duke University Computing Laboratory
    - Instruction Totals, 1962-1964
    - Maintenance Totals, 1962-1964
    - Supported Totals, 1962-1964
    - Unsupported Totals, 1962-1964
    - Annual Summaries, 1963-1964
  - Triangle Universities Computation Center (Box 5)
    - Memos, 1946-1947
    - Systems, Share, 1967
    - Minutes, 1967-1969
    - 1970-1971
    - Teleprocessing, 1967
    - Duke University vs. IBM, 1965-1967
  - National Science Foundation proposal, Duke University and Triangle Universities Computation Center, 1968
  - Long Range Computer Planning Committee
  - National Science Foundation grant proposals
  - Computing Laboratories summaries, 1964-1966
  - IBM proposal, background materials, June 1963
  - Control Data proposal to Duke University, 1965
  - Research notes for a presentation made to Greek doctors
    Some materials in Greek. Includes rules for using a computer to phonetically transcribe Greek.
  - Duke University Computer Science Program, ca. 1970 (Box 6)
  - Triangle Universities Computing Center materials, miscellaneous, 1970-1972
  - Data processing and hospital administration
  - Statistical processing of sociological data
  - Judy Gabor files [relating to the Duke University Computing Center]
Related Material
Computation Center records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Computer Center records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Department of Computer Science records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Triangle University Computation Center records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Vice Chancellor for Data Processing records.
University Archives, Duke University.